Hi, welcome to a physionic full study
analysis. It's been about six months
since we've done one of these. So today
we're going to be going over a topic
that is incredibly contentious, which is
the effect that canola oil in this
instance has on inflammation. So what I
did is I pulled together every
randomized control trial that I could
find on the topic, which is I think
either nine or 10 studies. And we're
going to dissect each one of those
studies and come to a conclusion on the
effect that canola oil has on
inflammation. Uh I realize that this
video is going to be extremely long,
incredibly in-depth. So if you'd like to
quick skip to the conclusions, feel free
to do that. They are located at the end
and there are timestamps for you. If
you're not familiar with who I am, my
name is Nicholas Verhovven. I'm a PhD in
molecular medicine and this is what I
do. I open up studies, make them
accessible to you so that you can look
at the data, understand the rationale
for how scientists came to the
conclusions that they did, uh,
understand my rationale for how I got to
the conclusions that I did, as well as
openly disagree. Obviously, if you see
the data in a different light, then that
way at least you can make up your own
mind uh instead of just typing it into
Google or following some health
influencer that doesn't do this kind of
stuff. So, if uh you're in for the ride,
then welcome aboard. Uh like I said,
this is going to take a while. I've
actually been avoiding this study
analysis simply because I find it an
incredibly boring topic. um which I
realize for videos is not the great way
to start things out, but it is what it
is. So, let's get into these uh 10
studies. And like I said, there are
timestamps, so you can skip to whatever
study kind of fits your criteria of what
you'd like to learn about. And uh then
we'll get to some sort of conclusion.
So, here's a breakdown of what we're
going to be covering. We're going to be
looking at the immediate postconumption
of canola oil on inflammation. Then
we're going to be looking at long-term
consumption on inflammation. And then
there is a singular study. Keep in mind
I've pulled together every single
randomized control trial that I could
find on this topic. And there are 10 of
them to date. Uh if there's one that I
missed, then please post it below.
Again, it has to be an intervention
trial and it must be looking at canola
oil and it must be looking at
inflammation specifically
that looks at heated canola oil and the
effect that that has on inflammation.
And if you're part of my Physionic
Insiders membership, then I'll also be
extending this analysis uh to be looking
at improving canola oils effects, if
they're negative to a neutral uh
situation or if they're neutral or
positive, if you can potentially
increase uh canola oil's potency. So, if
you're interested in that access to the
full version, then just uh pop on over
to my Physionic Insiders membership,
which is uh linked in the description
box. So, like I mentioned, let's go over
in the immediate measures of
inflammation. Uh so, a big question that
pops up often is the funding and the
conflicts of interest and whatnot. So,
you will find in the description of this
video all of the funding sources and the
conflicts of interest that I've looked
into for each one of these studies. But
for an incredibly short like a snippet
of an understanding of the funding
source, uh you'll see here that the
funding is nonprofit funding for this
particular study. So, this study is
again an acute study. So, we're just
going to be looking at uh single
consumption of canola oil to see if uh
it has some sort of an effect. And they
have a bunch of different conditions.
So, for one, they included 20 29
participants. Uh this is a single blind
experiment. So, the participants did not
know what they were consuming, but the
researchers did. Uh there's no placebo.
I don't think any of the studies that we
look at in this investigation were
placebolinded. Um mainly because when it
comes to nutrition, it's kind of hard to
do placebolinding, but not impossible,
but it's uh usually less common than in,
you know, for example, supplement
research or some sort of drug
intervention or whatnot. Uh like I said,
it's acute duration. It's a crossover
design. And so these 29 women uh ages 53
to 54 generally healthy and they
included uh lean and overweight
individuals. So we're going to be
looking at that data and although it's a
small sample size 29 individuals
the beauty of it is the fact that it is
a crossover design. So each one of these
participants act as their own control.
Uh each one of these individuals consume
an olive oil meal, a canola oil meal, a
potato meal, all brand meal, and a cream
meal to identify what kind of an effect
it has on these inflammatory markers.
But we're not just going to be stopping
at the inflammatory markers. We're also
going to look at just a few other
indices that I thought I'd just th go
ahead and throw in here as well. Here's
a breakdown of their nutrition uh in
terms of the single meal that they
consume. Keep in mind there's just a
single meal.
So the overall of course there are going
to be differences. Just to be clear,
they didn't actually do any statistics
here. So I can't actually statistically
tell you, hey, there are differences
between these groups. That is
statistically confirmed. I think we're
pretty safe in assuming though that if
we're looking at like the brand meal in
energy intake, it's going to be uh less
than this cream meal. the uh olive oil
meal or the canola oil meal. Clearly,
these are about equivalent in terms of
energy intake and uh roughly equivalent
in carbohydrate intake, roughly
equivalent in protein intake. And then
fats is where obviously these diverge
quite a bit, but at least between these
three, they're roughly the same. So, we
probably shouldn't focus too much on
these two meals simply because they
don't tell us a whole lot of information
in terms of what we're interested in,
which is canola oil. And then we have
these two other comparisons that are
quite close to it in almost every regard
except for obviously maybe some of the
uh the saturated fats and unsaturated
fats are going to be different between
the groups, which of course makes sense
because well, that's the nature of that
specific oil. So, let's compare canola
oil versus olive oil and cream.
Here we're looking at the baseline
characteristics. I'm not going to focus
on this too much clearly here. We've got
a bunch of statistical comparisons. Just
for reference, uh, if you're not aware
of how statistics works in a really
basic sense, if these numbers under the
p value, so the p value indicates if
something is detected as statistically
significant or not detected as
statistically significant, then these p
values will fall under 0.05 if they are
statistically significant. So detected
as statistically significant if is if
the number is above that that means that
we do not detect an effect. So you can
see in the comparison of the lean women
versus the obese women or overweight
women you can see that there are clearly
some areas where they differ from one
another. It's not exactly shocking news.
uh a person who is, I don't know, 50
pounds or 100 pounds uh over the weight
of somebody else and has a lot more body
fat on them. Well, that has to reflect
in their BMI, for example. That has to
reflect in their body weight. That has
to reflect in their waist circumference
and it's going to reflect in some of
their other health metrics because
typically these individuals are not as
healthy as leaner individuals. So, it's
not a shock that we see differences
here. I'm not blowing blowing anyone out
of the water here, but that's not
actually what we're interested in. What
we're actually interested in is closer
to the actual metrics. So, again, I'm
going to be ignoring certain aspects of
these data. I'm showing it to you. Uh
I'll explain it kind of just generally,
but uh you can pause the video and look
at this data for yourself. Um what I'm
going to be focused on is specifically
canola oil because that's really the
only thing that we're investigating
here. So here we've got our canola oil
condition. We're looking at blood
glucose levels, triglyceride levels, HDL
levels, and insulin levels. And here we
get to see it over time. So after
consuming the meal, what happens to
their blood glucose levels? So in
general, not always, but in general, you
see a spike in blood glucose levels.
Again, all these diets have, if I can go
back here real quick, all these diets
have carbohydrates in them. So not
exactly a shock that they would see an
increase in uh in blood sugar levels.
Insulin levels of course compensate as
well. They have to knock down these
blood glucose levels so they'll rise as
well. Uh triglyceride levels, you know,
maybe slightly rise over that time. HDL
doesn't seem to budge. But you don't
have to necessarily focus on this. You
can also look at what's known as the
area under the curve, which is
considering all the movement, all the
change that's occurred in this graph can
be displayed into a single bar graph.
And you're going to see this a few times
throughout this study. So, just focus on
that if you want an easier time uh make,
you know, determining the differences.
The dark bars are the obese individuals.
The white bars or the clear bars are the
lean individuals. And what we're looking
for is differences from baseline.
Probably you're going to see differences
between the two groups, right? Uh simply
because well, we already know that
physiologically they're completely
they're very different from one another.
So that wouldn't be much of a shock. And
we see some of those differences as we
keep going through this. But uh what
we're most interested in is the
differences from the zero here, which is
the baseline. Are we going to be able to
tell some differences in the canola that
might be worrying in some some some form
or fashion? And here we generally see,
you know, a decrease in the canola
condition. But again, we're comparing
that against the olive oil and the cream
condition. We're not just looking at the
baseline. We also want to look at some
of these other conditions that are good
comparison conditions. And what we see
is there's no difference across the
board generally. Uh for triglycerides,
there's maybe a little bit less
triglycerides compared to like the cream
condition. Uh for insulin levels, we
don't see any changes whatsoever uh
compared to any condition, but
especially the two that we're most
interested in. And for HDL, I mean, it
already didn't show any differences just
across the board. So, that's also the
case for canola oil. Now, let's look at
the actual inflammatory metrics. So when
we're looking at inflammation, we can
assess inflammation a few different
ways, but one of the most common ways is
to look at interlucan 6, TNF alpha, so
tumor necrosis factor alpha. And then
there's a bunch of other cytoines. These
are proteins that are released by your
cells. If that's your endothelial cells,
your neurons, your micro ga, your
macrofasages, monocytes, T-C cells, all
these different cells, lit almost every
cell in your body has the ability to
release except for if it doesn't have a
nucleus, which certain cells don't, but
the vast majority of cells are able to
release uh interlucan 6 or TNF alpha.
And generally, these are called
pro-inflammatory cytoines. are proteins
that get released and they can attract
immune cells to that region and activate
the immune cells to then start to cause
uh significant damage to the surrounding
area. It's not like the immune cells are
there to specifically do that, but
because they're in this activated state,
they start to kind of wreak havoc on
everything around them. So typically
when you have let's say chronic
inflammation then you'll see these
changes in 6 and TNF alpha they could
have certainly looked at others as a
matter of fact we do have a few over
here like uh like interlucan 8 and in
general we so let's I guess we'll focus
on interlucan 6 first we don't see any
changes here there are differences uh
between the obese and lean so we've got
the p values here comparing the fats
comparing the carbs and comparing the
obese and lean And you can see it's
statistically significant for the uh
obese and lean individuals. So the
comparison between those two but again
our focus is on canola oil and uh we
don't see any effect on from canola oil
across these three main conditions that
we're comparing against. What about TNF
alpha? Again canola oil just absolutely
doesn't move at all. Uh so we don't see
any change you know even by comparison
to olive oil which may slightly decrease
but statistically speaking we don't see
any difference for the free fatty acids.
So this is the fat molecules. uh we
again don't see any differences and
you'd be able to identify some of this
stuff by the like asterisk or this study
actually has a bunch of different
comparisons that it does and uh it's
it's pretty confusing to keep you keep
track of it all but again I'm just
focusing on canola oil and just trying
to see okay well if we look at this bar
graph is there a big difference compared
to olive oil or the cream condition
especially for the lean individuals but
also for overweight individuals.
And so, for example, here you might
think, yeah, there's there's look at
this one. It's so much higher than maybe
this one over here. But if you look at
the I believe these are standard error
of the means. So, this tells you not
only the spread of the data, but also
the certainty of the result. And if
these are really wide, that creates a
significant uncertainty in the results.
So the true representation or
interpretation of this would be that
there is no statistically significant
difference between the conditions. Then
again we're also looking at free fatty
acids. So then you would have to go
through another layer of rationale to
understand okay well if free fatty acids
are different if we were to assume that
they are uh what does that mean? Well
doesn't necessarily mean anything. So
you'd have to understand some of the
other physiology that's occurring and
across the board interlucanate as well
no differences. Uh canola oil does not
seem to reduce or increase or anything
uh on any of these inflammatory metrics.
Now one of the critiques that is often
levied and maybe I should have a
separate section at the end of this
video to uh discuss some of the
critiques that have been brought up. One
of them is definitely the heating of oil
and in this scenario we're not talking
about the heating of oil. It's just been
applied
to the foods.
We see that uh the
addition of oil in these conditions can
lead to
changes in the cell itself. So, not just
increases in the cytoines that might be
released from the cell, but one of the
critiques is well, you've got the
subclinical
uh argument, the subclinical
inflammation that occurs. So, the to be
completely honest with you, I don't
fully understand what that means. This
is coming from somebody who has a PhD in
molecular medicine.
Words get thrown around sometimes, and I
honestly just don't think that people
even understand what they mean. Uh
because I've asked people in the past
like, "Okay, so what does that mean?"
And nobody's been able to give me an
actual answer. So I'm going to answer it
the best I can from a PhD perspective
that's done cell biology, molecular
biology, and that would be something
like the oxidation of the lipids or the
fats that are found inside of the cell.
So oxidative stress is a situation where
the cell is producing large amounts of
these damaging molecules called reactive
oxygen species and a small amount is
actually beneficial to the cell but
having an overacrruel of these reactive
oxygen species can ultimately lead to
damage to the surrounding structure of
the cell. So that could be your
mitochondria, that could be the cell
membrane, that could be the different
proteins, the different enzymes in uh in
the cell. And in this situation, we're
talking about uh lipids. So lipid
peroxidation,
which is the oxidation or the damage of
lipids. That could be in the cell
membrane, that could be within the the
membranes of the organels, that could be
throughout the cell. It doesn't really
matter. The point being that you're
getting damage to the structure within
the cell. And we're measuring here again
with canola. Same situation. We see no
differences. So there's no effect on
lipid peroxidation.
And then uh they threw in a measure for
cortisol. Again, no differences uh for
for cortisol. It seems like all the
meals, I guess you could say, decreased
cortisol. But the main point being that
there are no differences across the
board. I suppose uh one more quick thing
to jump in on here with uh to describe.
I should have done this before, but let
me do it right now. Um to give you a
little bit more specifics on these
meals. So yes, each one of these meals
was dominated by olive oil or potato
meal or all brand meal etc. Um let me
give you a bit more specifics. So the
potato meal is literally just potatoes.
uh the all brand meal is removed the
mashed potatoes and replaced it with all
brand and milk. And again, they're
trying to equate the calories as best
they can or the energy as best they can,
but they're just switching out the
components uh to make up that meal. The
cream meal is 1.6 g per kilogram of body
weight in cream. So, if you weigh 100
kg, you'd be consuming about 160 gram of
cream in that one meal. And they also
include the mashed potato, but uh they
made it with more water to adjust the
calories. The olive oil meal was 0.6 g
per kilogram of body weight in oil. So,
again, that would be 60 g of olive oil.
And the mashed potato is also made with
more water to adjust for calories. The
canola oil meal was identical to the
olive oil meal in that it was about 0.6
gram per kilogram in body weight of oil.
So if you weigh 100 kg that would be
again 60 g of uh this canola oil that's
added to the meal. All the meals were
the same. So mashed potatoes plus two
eggs uh with the addition of each
condition. So just a standardized meal.
And as we saw, they try to standardize
the calorie consumption as much as
possible. Okay, let's discuss long-term
consumption on inflammation. This is
where the uh bulk of the analysis is
going to be focused on. We've got eight
studies to go over, I believe. So, I'm
going to go through them relatively
quickly and uh each study has different
uh aspects about it. You know, some are
in like older individuals, some are in
overweight individuals, some people have
metabolic syndrome, etc., etc. So again,
I encourage you to check out the one
that fits your profile the best. And
just be aware that each study is going
to have strengths and limitations.
So we'll start out with study 402. This
is internal funding. Keep in mind that
these people have ulcerative colitis.
Quick correction on this drawing. So
there's no sunflower oil condition. Uh
some of the other studies look at like
sunflower oil or safflower oil and some
other types of oils. We're only focused
on olive oil and canola oil here. So,
just ignore this condition. In this
scenario, it's 32 men and women, mostly
women, 35 to 36 years old with
ulcerative colitis and they were
overweight. It's not placeboc
controlled, which of course is ideal,
but uh unfortunately in it's not common
in nutrition studies to have a placebo
control. It's single blind, so the
participants did not know what they were
consuming, but the researchers knew uh
the assessment. There's a three-week
treatment. So, uh because it's crossover
design, so in this situation, this is a
extra virgin olive oil. And if let's say
11 of these people were randomly
assigned to olive oil, then they would
consume that olive oil for three weeks.
And then from there they would be
consuming 50 milliliters of uh extra
virgin olive oil or 50 milliliters of
canola oil just to be clear. And then so
let's say 11 people out of these 32 get
randomized to olive oil. They consume
the 50 milliliters of olive oil every
day. And then uh they do a twoe wash out
to essentially bring them back down to
baseline and kind of wash out whatever
residual effects might be occurring from
olive oil consumption. And then after
those two weeks of the wash out period,
then they uh get put on the canola oil.
And then they do the same thing, three
weeks of canola oil for 50 milliliters
consumption. And then they take
measurements throughout that period. So
it's a crossover design. They've got a
smaller number of participants.
Definitely an advantage. You get to
control for the genetics, for example.
you get to control for bunch of other
things because the the same person is
their own control which is uh very nice
to see. Um there are advantages and
disadvantages to to that. Um in fact
I've covered them in my course on how to
read studies if you want to check that
out. It's also linked in the
description. Okay so let's get into the
specifics of how they went about this.
They randomized 40 individuals into the
canola oil condition or the extra virgin
olive oil condition and they did lose a
few people on followup. Um so they ended
up with the 32 individuals that I
mentioned earlier. Now let's go into
the groups in their order. Um again keep
in mind it's the same individual. So in
the first 3 weeks, the group that was in
the in the um EVVO first and then canola
oil or canola oil and then EVVO, there
were uh no differences across the board.
So this is just looking at some baseline
uh characteristics to identify hey maybe
maybe this baseline difference between
the groups is the real reason why uh we
see some sort of change. But in this
case, we don't see anything of that
nature. All right, let's get into it.
Uh, I realize this looks like a bunch of
numbers. Don't worry about it. It's
actually very easy to read here. Um, so
I'm going to detail these for you. Right
here, we've got three different P
values. The P values correspond to
different comparisons. The PAT here
corresponds to the treatment effect. So,
is there an effect in general? uh not
specific to canola oil, not specific to
EVO. The PBC condition here is a
comparison of uh within each group. So
looking within the EVO or within the uh
canola oil condition. Then comparing
between the groups is the PCP.
PCP. Oh man, it's a it's a bad
combination of letters. uh hopefully
they don't get too high. Okay, so PCP
over here is the comparison of the EVO
versus uh canola oil. So you see the P
values again the cutoff is 0.05
where here's a quiz question, here's a
trivia question. Where do you see an
effect? It's over here right in this
column. And it's just these two
situations over here. So we're looking
at the PAT which is an overall just is
there an effect
and here we're looking at ariththraite
sedimentation rate which is a metric of
inflammation. Uh we also have high
sensitivity uh C reactive protein
another measure of inflammation. We're
aware of tumor necrosis factor alpha
unless you skip the last study. Uh so
we've got the three measures right here
and for these two we do see that there
is a difference. So something occurs uh
but is we don't have enough statistical
power here at least to identify any sort
of difference if it's the EVO or the the
canola oil and there's no difference
between the two groups. So on and that's
also true for TNF alpha. So across the
board and if anything if anything uh we
see yeah we just don't see any changes
whatsoever. I mean you also have these
uh massive standard deviations. If those
are standard deviations, let me quick
check. Yes, those are standard
deviations. So they are pretty massive I
will say. I mean having a value 17.89
plus plus or minus standard deviation of
85.6 six. That indicates to me that uh
they needed a lot more either a lot more
participants or they needed better uh
measurement of the uh TNF alpha values
or or
you could have a group of individuals
that are experiencing a higher or lower
TNF alpha versus another group which
creates a lot of uh deviation in the
results. We don't see as much when
looking at the EVO condition here. uh
but we do see it in some of these other
metrics as well. Anyway, the point being
statistically speaking, there are no
differences in uh inflammation. Okay,
let's get into the next study. I'm going
to have to make a correction here as
well. Um I don't actually make my
PowerPoints anymore. I put out a uh
description of what I need put together
and uh someone else actually puts it
together and unfortunately
they made a few mistakes which I should
have caught. So I'm going to correct
them uh in this discussion right now.
So, uh, study 403
in, uh, this study is publicly funded,
uh, and has no conflicts of interest, no
direct conflicts of interest at least.
Uh, in this situation, we've got an
olive oil condition. So, this is refined
olive oil versus canola oil. And in this
situation, they're talking about 25
milliliters uh, consumed. This is a
longer study. It's a six-w weekek
treatment, so that's all correct. It was
also randomized.
However, it and it was no blinding. So,
no placebo, no blinding. Um, however,
these people did not have ulcerative
colitis. So, I think this was from the
previous uh description. These people
had uh cardiovascular disease and were
overweight. So, this is the part that
needs to change. Uh also this uh was 48
participants and it was mostly men. Just
to be clear, this is not a crossover
design. It's a parallel design. Uh
meaning that you have one group that
only consumes canola oil and then the
other group only consumes olive oil and
then they do comparisons across the
board. Uh this was a six week treatment,
so about double the length of the
previous study. Okay. Uh the composition
of the oils, I don't really need to go
through it. Obviously, there going to be
differences. They're different oils, so
they're going to be differences. Um, but
here you go. You've got a breakdown of
the composition,
[Music]
the way it was like the actual flow, the
diagram of how things worked out. They
had 48 individuals that they randomized,
24 to one group, 24 to another group.
They lost a few on follow-up, 22 were
analyzed, and 20 were analyzed in this
one. And ultimately, that led us to
these baseline characteristics. I
already explained why why a person would
want to look at baseline characteristics
to see if there are any inherent
differences between the groups. This is
especially true if you're looking at uh
parallel groups and we see the p value
here no differences across the board. So
the groups are roughly the same. Uh so
then we can look at the comparisons of
what happens when you consume canola oil
versus olive oil, refined olive oil. Uh
so in this situation we're looking at uh
body weight at baseline so before
consuming the oils and then 6 weeks
later and we can see that there are no
differences. Uh so and there are no
differences between the groups either.
So largely body weight stayed the same.
Uh BMI obviously is going to stay
roughly the same. Physical activity is
another kind of important metric that
people might be interested in. Uh again
no differences.
Now, here is where we're looking at the
overall dietary intake of these
individuals at baseline. Then six weeks
later, we're interested, which is a good
question as to if there are differences
between the groups in their nutrition.
And now, if you have enough participants
in a study, uh it usually all that stuff
kind of washes out because everybody
kind of just follows the mean or the
average.
uh but
or corrects to the mean or corrects to
the average. But in this scenario uh
with a smaller sample size when you're
talking about you know just 40
individuals um you know it's it can be
important to look at their nutritional
profile and see if there are any
differences. So it's a good thing that
they looked at this. Uh in fact these
little crosses here are not religiosity.
They are uh changes from baseline. So
the p values here indicate changes
between the olive oil group and the
canola oil group. But the crosses here
indicate changes from baseline to 6
weeks later. So like total fat for
example increased slightly for the olive
oil group and it also increased for the
canola oil group but ultimately there
were no differences between the groups.
Now, obviously, that's not too much of a
shock, right? If uh 25 milliliters of
olive oil and canola oil, uh yeah, it's
going to have an impact um on your your
fat consumption considering they're both
complete fat. Um the other change let's
see monounsaturated fats you know again
not a shock considering both of them
have uh different compositions of fat
especially olive oil is well known for
its monounsaturated fats and that's it
you know that I mean you see these
changes but generally oh I guess
omega-3s
um there was in omega-3s for the canola
oil condition but not for the
olive oil condition. Uh however the end
result was the same that there were no
differences in uh omega-3 consumption
between the the two groups. So
equivalent at the end.
Okay. So let's look at these values
again. We've got some values here that
are not necessarily related to
inflammation, but there are also some
that are related to inflammation. Here
we've got the delta. So okay, I'll I'll
break this down. total cholesterol, LDL
cholesterol, small dense LDL, got HDLC,
total cholesterol divided by HDLC,
triglycerides, LPLA,
which is this uh inflammation marker
lipoprotein associated phospholipase A2
and then we've got interlucan 6, which
we've already gone over and then we've
got complement components. So these
proteins are also involved in the immune
system and play a big role in the
compliment system. I'm not going to
explain what the compliment system is.
Uh
yeah I yeah I won't explain it. It's
it's a it's in very basic terms it's a a
series of proteins that can work
together in complement essentially and
uh activate the immune system. So,
they're kind of this uh other pathway by
which our immune system functions.
Believe it or not, uh immunity and
inflammation and whatnot are incredibly
complex processes. That's why you have
people that study it exclusively,
immunologists.
So, but for our purposes, what we need
to know is that these are also
inflammation.
So we're looking at different metrics of
inflammation other than this uh
interlucan 6.
And then we've got our olive oil group,
canola oil group, got our baseline 6
weeks later. And then the delta value.
So the amount of change from one to 6
weeks later, from baseline to 6 weeks
later. And then we're looking at
differences uh between the groups. If
there's again a cross, that means
there's differences uh at baseline
compared to 6 weeks later. But the
actual p value here indicates the
differences between the olive oil group
versus the canola oil group. Okay. So
what do we see? Well, let's focus on the
canola oil group here first. There's
only uh one change and that change is a
decrease in interlucan 6. Uh if we look
at but there are no changes on like this
uh lipoprotein associate phospholipase
2. Again, just to confirm that's another
factor involved in cardiovascular
disease, but also inflammation. And then
the compliment proteins don't change.
The canola oil group, we look down here
and we see that there's a statistically
significant uh decrease in this
inflammation marker, this lipoprotein
associate phospholippase
A2. I can never remember the name of
that. And there are no changes in
interlucan 6. So uh there's you know a
non-significant decrease but it's
technically we should say that it's
there's no difference. On the other hand
when we compare between the two groups
there's no differences across the board
for the most part except for some of the
inflammation markers. So like interlucan
6, there's a statistically significant
difference between canola oil and olive
oil indicating that uh the canola oil uh
had I guess you could say worse results
than the olive oil. I just want to
contextualize that correctly. Yes,
technically that's true, but it's not
like uh canola oil increased
inflammation. It just kept it neutral.
Uh on the other hand, the olive oil was
the one that actually decreased the
inflammation from this one metric. But
we can do the exact same story when
we're looking at this LPPLA too. In this
case, it is statistically significant
difference and the olive oil condition
actually doesn't see any change. Slight
increase, but in all reality again, we
would interpret this as no difference
and or a neutral effect. And here we see
that there's a reduction uh with the
canola oil. So the same story is just
flipped to the other side. But again,
we're not going to extol all the we're
we're not going to suddenly blame olive
oil and say that that has tremendous
negative effects on your inflammation.
So they kind of uh they kind of flip
sides, you know, both ways one way or
another. uh there's a a decrease in an
inflam inflammation marker for olive oil
and there's a decrease in inflammation
marker for the canola oil condition. All
right, ladies and gentlemen, let's go on
to the next study. Study 404. Internal
funding, as far as I'm aware, no direct
conflicts of interest either. Uh this
one was correctly laid out finally. Um,
so we've got 81 women, uh, 58 years old,
uh, were overweight with type 2
diabetes, uh, so not in great metabolic
health. They were randomized. This is
non placebo control just like most of
the others, and no blinding. So the
participants were aware of what they
were consuming. They were consuming
olive oil, canola oil, or sunflower oil,
and they consumed 30 grams of each every
day. Uh, this is parallel design. So,
we've got a group of people in the
sunflower oil, a group of people in the
canola oil, and a group of people in the
olive oil. And they were compared
against each other at baseline, and then
again at the end of the 8 weeks, so uh
two months later.
Here we've got the 81 individuals
randomized. And here we've got the
number of people that ended up coming
out in the end. um you can see why some
of the people were excluded over that
time. If we look at the fatty acid
composition, I'm actually not really
going to go over this because you can
read it for yourself. Saturated fats,
monounsaturated fats, poly
polyunsaturated fats, different carbon
chain lengths. Uh so if you rec if you
were to type in like C16 for example
into like Google or AI or whatever, then
you would end up with a name for that
fatty acid. that fatty acid is palatate
and so on and so forth for each one of
these. Um here we're looking at
polyunsaturated fats. Here we're looking
at monounsaturated fats. But here we've
got everything in conjunction kind of
together. Uh again this is obvious
stuff. Obviously there there's going to
be differences in the composition of
fats in olive oil, canola oil, and
sunflower oil. That's what makes them
unique. Okay. Now in terms of the
baseline characteristics here again
we've got the three groups we've got the
p value here and we can just quick look
at this scan it for any sort of
differences you know maybe a getting
close to statistically significant for
polyunsaturated fats maybe dietary fiber
intake maybe the canola oil might be
slightly higher than than the sunflower
oil but uh it's still not statistically
significant uh polyans saturated fat.
Again, that kind of stuff is not that
shocking because, keep in mind, they're
consuming completely different fats. Uh,
not maybe not a whole lot. 30 grams,
it's it's a good amount, but it's not a
massive amount, but it's probably enough
to shift some of these values. Okay.
Then the actual changes that occur in
relation to these different fats
including with uh diet with the status
and cons in consideration. Okay. And
here we're looking at the values during
the study. So this is a baseline and
here we're looking. So I guess what I
should have said before is that these
values were not including the oils. So I
misspoke earlier. Uh this is the
updated. So during the study, this is
while they're consuming or after they've
consumed the oils. And here we do see
that things are statistically
significantly different. However, uh
nothing else is. So the fiber actually
becomes non-statistically significantly
different. But uh only the percentages
of these different fats monounsaturated
and polyunsaturated
lead to changes which is expected.
Okay. Now here the researchers do
something that really annoys me. Uh they
make it incredibly difficult to read
this and the reason why I mention that
is because they don't report any p
values and on top of that they don't
give us any sort of symbols or anything
to indicate what's statistically
significant. is really is a pet peeve of
mine when it comes to reading research
because then you have to sit there and
dig through uh what they wrote and try
to figure out what you know P values
correspond to what. But what I can tell
you is well I guess I'll walk you
through this first. We got fasting uh
blood sugar here first and then we've
got uh the
how do you pronounce that? uh
malendahhide
there we go my
malendihide or MDA which is a metric of
lipid peroxidation so kind of a
byproduct of uh lipid peroxidation which
is what we discussed in one of the
previous studies so this is an
indication of what I would consider
again nobody's ever really defined it
but what I would consider as subclinical
uh evidence of uh inflammation or damage
that's occurring to the cells because
you have this oxidative stress that's
occurring. So greater levels of MDA
would indicate greater oxidative stress
and greater damage to the cells. Then
you've got insulin homir
insulin resistance uh measure which
includes fasting blood sugar as well as
insulin and then C reactive protein
which we've gone over before. So just
from the what the researchers write, I
can tell you that the olive oil, canola
oil, and sunflower oil conditions, none
of them changed for any of the metrics
except for CRP. Uh for CRP, if I could
quick check my notes here, olive oil and
canola oil saw changes in C reactive
protein. So this change here, minus3.2
and minus 2.5 are reductions in the C
reactive protein. But as far as I'm
aware, well actually we can actually
look at that next.
Uh this is looking at the exact same
metrics but now they're breaking it up
by intergroup analysis p value. So
looking at uh the olive oil baseline
versus after baseline. So after 8 weeks
of being on olive oil, you know, same
thing for canola oil, same thing for
sunflower oil in each one of these
conditions. And that's where we get this
uh effect of uh this change has a p
value attributed to it but for some
reason they decide to separate it out
and put it into this uh table instead of
putting it in here. Yes, I find that
highly annoying.
Anyway, statistically significant
differences reductions in C reactive
protein. And then they do another
analysis which is between groups. So
doing the comparison of olive oil versus
canol can canola oil versus sunflower
oil and we see it is statistically
significant here as well. They find a I
guess technically they find statistical
significance as well for homir but uh
it's just barely there and this C also
indicates that it's a non-parametric
result which means that oh man do I
really want to go into that. Um, it
means that the data is skewed in a
nonnormal way. I realize that for
somebody that doesn't really have a
statistics background, that doesn't
really mean anything. Um, it just means
that you need a specialized statistical
test to detect an effect. And they do
detect that there's an effect between
the groups. But when you compare at
least baseline to and then when you look
at the intergroup as in looking baseline
versus 8 weeks later there's no
difference across the group. So you know
it really just depends on like which
test is more appropriate to interpret
and whatnot in this situation. We have
clear results for C reactive protein and
we have really dubious results when it
comes to home IR but you know anybody
with a statistics background could
easily disagree but for sure I don't
think anybody would disagree that C
reactive protein at least decreases with
olive oil and canola oil and that's
confirmed again by the between groups
comparison. Okay, let's get into study
406. Uh for this one this is uh industry
funding so just be aware of that. You
can check out more details in the
description. Uh here's a breakdown of
the study how it was done. It is again
randomized, non placebo, no blinding. Uh
this is a crossover design. So it's
three different conditions and it's
crossover design. So it's a little bit
of a complex design in terms of like
what they consumed and whatnot. Um but
the participants consumed a standard
western diet as a base diet which was
about 15% protein, 50% carbohydrates and
35% dietary fat. And
then they consumed each oil for four
weeks, did a wash out for four to eight
weeks. So it says four-week wash out
here, but it's four to eight weeks of
wash out. So a minimum of four weeks
we'll say and then return to include a
new oil. So back to that standard
western diet including uh the the next
oil. Again they were randomly assigned
to the high oleic canola oil, the flax
seed oil plus canola oil or the butter
plus olive oil plus vegetable oil plus
sunflower oil. Uh which is this blended
and they tried to do like a one to one.
So basically equate the same amount of
oil in each condition. They did consume
a pretty sizable amount. It was
something like with let's say 100 gram
of fat consumed, they would consume
about 70 gram of oil. So the majority or
a good portion of the fat that they
consumed throughout the day was from
these oils. Uh this was in men and women
but mostly women 47 years of age
overweight with high cholesterol uh as
their one notable uh metric of ill
health. And again here we're talking
because it's a crossover design. It it
slightly makes I shouldn't even say
slightly. It does a good job of making
up for the fact that we've got a small
sample size. Still, you know, it'd be
great to have even more individuals, of
course. So, just from the get-go, I'd
like to say this is kind of a messy
study. I mean, they're adding butter,
olive oil, vegetable oil plus sunflower
oil, flax seed oil plus canola oil, or
high oleic canola oil. I mean, it's kind
of like it's just kind of all over the
place. This is not a very well-designed
study. You can tell immediately from
this alone that it's not a very
well-designed study. But hey, I said
that I'd include all the studies, so
this is what I'm doing. Here's a
breakdown of the western diet. Then the
addition of the high oleic or rape seed
oil diet and the flax seed and high
oleic rape seed oil diet. Okay, let's
get into the macronutrient breakdown for
these uh diets. So just to be clear,
this western diet here is the butter
plus olive oil plus uh vegetable oil.
This like blended oil condition. Um, I
don't know why they're calling it
specifically a western diet, but I mean
obviously the background is largely a
western diet, but uh that's also the
case for these other conditions. So
again, it's a messy study and it's about
to get messier. I can promise you that
much. So these are the baseline values.
Uh if you're hoping for statistical
analyses on these, none were given. So
we're just going to have to look at it
and say, "Yeah, there are no, you know,
there are differences. there are no
differences uh etc etc.
Um baseline characteristics
here we've got everyone remember it's
the same individuals so we don't have
like three separate groups we just have
the same individuals they're looking at
age body weight height BMI total
cholesterol and some of the metrics that
we've already looked at LDL cholesterol
HDL cholesterol and trial glycerols or
triglycerides C reactive protein for
inflammatory metrics interlucan 6 we
should be well aware of that VCAM ICAM
and E selectin Those are all proteins
that are found on like endothelial cells
that line your blood vessels and they're
heavily implicated in inflammation of
your vascule.
So the more of them typically that means
that you have greater uh it's linked to
greater inflammation and is linked to
greater risk of cardiovascular disease.
And here they also did some corateed
intimidia thickness measurements. I have
to say I find this absolutely laughable.
Um, but they did it anyway. So, we get a
measure of their plaque buildup in their
arteries. I'm going to explain why it's
laughable in just a little bit.
Uh, looking at the values after, like at
the end of the four weeks
of each diet, you see the uh,
cholesterol or total cholesterol levels.
And you you can obviously read it for
yourself. uh but ultimately we're
looking for this p value to indicate
differences between the groups. So here
again we're seeing some comparisons and
we're seeing that there's drops in total
cholesterol LDL cholesterol that's why
we've got statistical significance. Uh I
guess to interpret this if the the
letters here are the same as the other
groups that means there's no difference.
um if they're different then that means
there is a difference and so this p
value indicates there's an overall
statistically significant difference
then you could look to the letters to
identify okay where is that difference
because we have three conditions so we
need to know which condition is
different from which condition uh if we
had just two then we would know that
there's a difference so we can just look
at the comparison between the two we
don't need the letters so for example
for LDL cholesterol we see that there's
an A here we see a B here and we see a B
here. That indicates that these two are
the same, but they're different from
this western diet condition. There's a
drop in LDL cholesterol with this high
oleic oil condition and the flax seed
high oleic oil condition.
Uh HDL, you can do the same thing.
There's no difference between these two.
there is a drop in HDL with the flax
seed plus high oleic uh and you can see
that statistically confirmed the same is
true for looking at some of these ratios
nonHDL cholesterol uh we see that
there's a a drop in so these are all
different right A B C that means that
this is at the highest point so this one
didn't change or at least presumably
didn't change this one did change it
dropped so in high oleic condition. So
the high
the canola oil condition, we see that
there's a drop in non-HDL cholesterol,
which isn't a shock because we already
saw a drop in LDL cholesterol. And then
there's a slightly greater drop in the
flax seed plus high oleic uh condition
or canola oil condition. Same thing as
rape seed, by the way. It's just that
the name's been changed because rape
seed sounds incredibly aggressive.
uh we can look at the exact same values
but now in bar graph form and again
across the board. I don't even need to
really define what each uh graph is. I
guess I will real quick. So this uh dark
one is the western diet. This one is the
high the gray one is the dark or the
high oleic rape seed oil or canola oil.
And the white one here is the final one.
So the uh high oleic acid plus uh
flaxseed oil. So the third condition and
across the board we see I mean we
already went over these data. So uh when
you do comparisons some of them are the
same some of them are different but
overall the point is that the western
diet tends to do worse uh across the
board.
But what we're most interested in is
obviously the effect that we see on
inflammation. So what does inflammation
tell us? We've got a bunch of metrics
here. C reactive protein, interlucan 6,
and these three different markers or
proteins that are found on typically
endothelial cells in our vascule.
And we see that there's uh no difference
across the board,
you know. Oh. Oh, I guess I'm sorry.
There's one difference the E select in
here. So A, A, B and B. So the canola
oil only condition uh was kind of in the
middles maybe a slight uh decrease in
this e select. reduced inflammation in
this situation but uh not oh I'm sorry
actually this is uh this is dropped the
lowest um and then the flax seed and
high oleic condition was different from
the western diet uh just further just a
little bit higher than the just oleic
condition or just canola oil condition.
So canola oil outperformed the the at
least the western diet um even if it
might not be exactly different from uh
the uh flax seed condition.
Now as for the IMT the intermedia
thickness the reason why I find this
laughable is because we're talking about
a four-week study.
I I mean I got to admit this it's just
like ridiculous to me to even do this.
Um, I know that IMT is pretty sensitive.
When you're measuring corateed IMT, you
can do some sensitive metrics that
indicate
changes over, let's say, a year, maybe a
little less than a year, but four weeks.
I mean, unless you're expecting canola
oil or flax seed or the western diet to
increase plaque appreciably, like just
supercharge plaque production in in your
arteries in just a month. Um, it every
study that's been done on corateed IMT
has not looked at four weeks or at least
no serious studies that have looked at
corateed IMT have used four weeks. So, I
just I don't know. There's a bunch of
things about this study that I just find
irritating and uh poorly done. But the
conclusion here based on this poor data
is that uh the canola oil or at least
the other two oils. So canola oil or the
one with flax seed tended to outperform
the uh the one that was western diet
plus the other oils that was added in
mixture. All right, let's get into this
next study. Study 407. It's public
funding, but
uh there are some direct conflicts of
interest. So, check those out in the
description.
Uh here we've got a bunch of conditions.
Again, it's crossover design. Uh we've
got a bunch of different like hybrid
systems of uh looking at canola oil.
This one is heavily focused on canola
oil. So, we've got canola oil condition
and all of these. So I guess to give you
a background on the diets these are
isocaloric meaning that they consume the
same amount of uh calories uh across the
board on the base diet which was a
standard western diet 50% carbohydrates
35% dietary fat 18% of that fat came
from these oils. So that's the amount
given and 15% protein. Canola oil was
here. Then they've got a high oleic
version, so more monounsaturated fats in
this canola oil. Then they've got a
canola oil plus the addition of omega-3,
so enriched with docoexoninoic acid,
which is an omega-3. And then they've
got this corn saff, which is the corn
oil plus an equal proportion of
safflower oil. And then flax saff, which
is flax seed oil plus safflower oil.
The oils were consumed in smoothie form.
So 30 grams per smoothie and consumed uh
twice per day. So I guess in total about
60 gram of each oil. Must have been
delicious smoothies for sure.
101 men and women 49 years of age
overweight borderline metabolic
syndrome. So kind of like definitely
pre-diabetic
and beyond. uh four weeks treatment with
a two to four week wash out uh at least
a minimum of two weeks and up to four
weeks of that wash out period before
jumping onto the next diet. So we'll see
see them in four-week increments.
Here we've got a breakdown of the
individuals. 170 randomized uh 130
individuals were assessed for
eligibility and 101 were assessed uh
were actually included in the study
itself. And here we've got a breakdown
of uh the diets for each condition. Here
they're uh breaking down so this is the
baseline metrics and they're breaking it
down by men and women.
And believe it or not, shockingly,
uh, the men weigh more than the women.
The waist circumference is bigger for
the men than the women. I mean, not
exactly shocking news on that front. So,
uh, yeah, that doesn't that doesn't
exactly uh really tell us a whole lot.
It just tells us that men and women are
different, which is not a revelation.
Um, the height is funny because they
measured it in meters and they don't see
a statistically significant difference.
I wonder if they had just changed this
metric or I don't know what happened
here, but it's seems odd that there's
not a statistically significant
difference in the height between men and
women when we know on a population level
that men are uh taller than women. But
maybe this sample was just very similar
in that regard somehow. So interesting,
but something to point out. Okay, so I
just wanted to quick add this. This is
overall fat mass or I should say android
fat mass, which is a type of fat mass
that tends to be more inflammatory and
more destructive. And we can see here
again, you're comparing these different
letters and you can see the statistical
significance indicated by the the
asterisk here. But uh the point being
here that these two are roughly the
same. So the men and overall which isn't
going to be a huge shock because uh the
men make up what how much of the study
half of the study participants and the
women although it's not statistically
significant you can see that they also
seem to decrease their android fat mass.
And that's for the canola group which is
probably the most telling group. Uh, I
understand that we've got other canola
groups here as well, but really we
should be probably focused on this one
because this one has been, you know,
they've added monounsaturated fats and
this one they've added uh omega-3s
and generally we see not huge
differences across the board, but again
we're talking about four-week
consumption and we're looking at this
random metric of android fat mass and
just kind of okay, I guess we we see a
little bit of changes uh that happen
more for men than they do for women, but
uh doesn't really seem to matter all
that much. Okay, this is a bit of a
complex way of showing if canola oil or
any of these conditions have an effect
on inflammation. Uh the only metric that
they really measure for inflammation is
C reactive protein. are also included
including Android fat mass or the delta
in Android fat mass or the change in
Android fat mass and all they're doing
is finding an association. They're not
even trying to find if it really has an
effect here. Um I'm assuming that the
answer is that they didn't really have
an effect. And if you look at the
association, so here we've got an
associative marker or uh an indication
of the correlation, the association
between CRP and each one of these
different conditions. So canola canola
oleic etc etc. So if this is very low so
let's say below 0.1
then there's essentially no association
but if it's anything above that 0.2
definitely 0.4 definitely 0.6 0.8 would
be a really strong association so on and
so forth then typically the p value will
also indicate that it's statistically
significant. So for example, CRP is
associated is weakly associated because
this is above 0.1. It's, you know, 0.28,
which still isn't super strong, but it's
a weak association. There is an
association. It's just weak. Uh, and it
is statistically significant. So Android
fat mass at baseline is associated with
C reactive protein. Not a huge shock.
We've actually known that fat mass, the
more fat the p person has on their body,
the more
uh their inflammation metrics tend to
increase. Uh however, once we start
looking at some of these other metrics,
looking at like uh canola oil or
whatever it might be on and including
changes in android fat mass from
baseline, we see that this association
is just about nil. I mean, we don't see
any association. Even this, which you
know could potentially be a weak
association, is not statistically
significant. They don't actually report
the the P values here, which I find
interesting. Uh but whatever the point
is that there's no association between
canola oil and reducing C reactive
protein. And that's really the big
takeaway here. Again, why they focused
on associations and tried to add this
other metric of android fat mass, I
don't really know, but that's the the
choice that they made. Um, in addition,
they only used 54 individuals from this
uh from this group. Remember, they had,
I believe, and yeah, 101 individuals in
the study, and they only ended up
including 54 for this associative data.
So beats me. I don't know. But the point
here being the overall point is that CRP
is not reduced with canola oil or is not
associated with reduction uh from canola
oil consumption. All right, let's get
into uh one of the final studies here
looking at study 409 as internal funding
and no direct conflicts of interest, but
it's still a pretty bad study. Okay, so
in this situation, we finally have a
placebo group, and that placebo group is
canola oil. Uh, this is kind of a weird
study. It seems just like a complete
waste of money, but maybe I'm just being
overly negative. I don't know. Um, so
we've got 50 men and women, mostly
women, 35 to 60 years old, overweight
with type two diabetes, and they're
randomized to either consume a enriched
canola oil with
tootrienol, which is a type of vitamin E
or a subclass of vitamin E, 15
milliliters a day of this canola oil, or
they were randomized to placebo, which
is canola oil without this subclass of
vitamin E had and they consumed them for
8 weeks and it was double blind which is
great. So the the rigorousness of the
study design is great. It's just the
point of the study is difficult to
figure out uh because they're comparing
canola oil versus canola oil. So
the actual study aim in this situation
is going to tell us if T3, this addition
of this tootrienol
has an effect on canola oil or the
whatever effects that we experience with
canola oil, is it going to improve them
or worsen them or whatever? But the
point is that this study is designed to
identify an effect of tocotatrienol, not
to identify an effect of canola oil. Why
did I add it? The question might be,
well, I added it because we can at least
still eyeball some differences from just
canola oil. So, you know what's funny is
we're not that interested in this
condition. We're actually interested in
what happens in the placebo condition as
we'll see. Okay. Okay, so the baseline
uh characteristics between the groups,
there are no differences, at least based
off of the measures that they uh used
here, which is pretty standard.
Uh then we've got the dietary intakes uh
before and after the 8 weeks. And uh we
don't see any differences here. This is
kind of messy, but there's no
differences across the board uh between
these different uh conditions.
And here we're looking at the or a few
different metrics. We're going to focus
on the ones that matter the most like
Nitric oxide which is extremely
important in cardiovascular disease.
Nitric oxide will open your blood
vessels and will tend to reduce blood
pressure. uh on the other hand uh serum
high sensitivity C reactive protein uh
tends to is this uh this inflammation
marker that is often used. There's CRP
and then there's a high sensitivity
version. It's become a lot more common
to use this high sensitivity uh version.
And then we've got these other metrics
that really just don't matter that much,
at least not for uh inflammation like
micro albammen and urine volume and
urine creatinine. Maybe in like severe
pathology, you might be curious about
that kind of stuff. If you're let's say
a physician and you're interested in
like kidney health, for example, then
you might be interested in the albumin
levels or the different protein uh
excretions or the urine volume, things
of that nature. But for looking at
inflammation, uh, this doesn't tell us a
whole lot of information. So, we'll
focus on these two areas. So, for the
serum n, we've got our p values here.
So, looking at the differences uh
between these conditions.
Yeah. So, P1 is the within group
comparison. So looking at week 0 versus
week 8 and then we've got our P2 which
is over here uh which is the between
groups comparisons. So looking at serum
N O we see that there's no difference
you know week 0 to week 8 for the
enriched canola oil or for the pure
canola oil then and then obviously no
differences uh when we're looking at the
between groups comparisons on the other
hand when we look at the high
sensitivity CRP we see there is a
statistically significant decrease in
high sensitivity CRP in the enriched
condition and we do not see that effect
in the pure canola condition and in fact
the between groups condition indicates
there's statistically significant effect
between these two groups. So the
enrichment of canola oil actually
slightly improves the reduction in high
sensitivity CRP. So, I just want to be
clear here again because just because we
don't see a statistically significant
effect in one and we do in the other,
that doesn't mean that canola oil
doesn't have or doesn't mean that canola
oil has a negative for us. I just want
to be clear on that. So, what it
actually trends towards is an
improvement. But again, statistically
speaking, there's no difference.
So the takeaway here from this rather
odd study is that
uh canola oil does not seem to increase
inflammation and uh that enriching
canola oil with T3
uh leads to slightly improved reductions
in inflammation or actually leads to
reductions in inflammation from uh
canola oil consumption. Okay, we're on
to our final study uh for before we get
into heated canola oil and see if
heating canola oil to an extreme degree
uh leads to changes in inflammation as
well. So, study 410. This is mixed
funding and did uh include some
conflicts of interest. So, again, uh
check that out in the description. All
right, so we've got our uh two
conditions. Well, I guess no, I guess we
only have one condition actually. uh
we're looking at an experimental diet
and this experimental diet participants
consumed similar food items uh to the
control diet. So there's no placebo
group but there's actually a control
diet. That control diet is just
regularly commercially available food
items with a standard fat composition.
That's what the study has to provide.
The difference so I guess what we're
taking away here is that we've got two
diets. They're identical except for the
experimental diet in addition to
consuming those particular foods also
consumed or replaced saturated fats in
that ex in that diet in the control diet
with polyunsaturated fats and uh mostly
with canola oil mostly with uh
polyunsaturated fats. So it creates
uniformity except for the fat
composition in the experimental diet.
Kind of explained that poorly, but
hopefully that made sense. Uh we've got
115 men and women uh between 25 and 70
years of age. Uh they were o and the
average was 55 overweight and uh had
mildly high uh cholesterol, blood
cholesterol levels. There was no placebo
but there was a control group which
probably should have been shown on this
end. Uh and it was double blind. So the
researchers did know uh the participant
conditions and the participants didn't
know which condition that they were in.
Uh this was 8 weeks and it was parallel
design again control versus
experimental. So, anytime you see
experimental, just know that it has more
of these uh unsaturated fats, these uh
uh omega-6 unsaturated fats.
And here we've got the different uh
basis for these different diets. Uh
again, I'm not going to go through every
single aspect of this. Uh you can see
there's some similarity and then there's
some areas where they replaced it. So,
like liquid margarine versus butter, for
example. uh the canola oil versus olive
oil, like stuff like that. But for the
most part, everything else was the same.
I I mean, really, you look at this and
you just think to yourself, why? This
just looks so messy. It just looks so
bad. I Maybe it's just me. Let me know
if you if you've like completely checked
out. I just be curious if you haven't.
uh when you look at this, does this does
this immediately seem intuitive to you?
Because it doesn't to me. So, you have
to sit there and be like, "Okay, what am
I looking at?" All right. So, we've got
all the metrics that they measure here
for baseline characteristics, age, uh
sex, smokers, BMI, you know, all that
stuff over here. We've got some of these
uh these uh different like uh high
sensitivity CRP which is going to be the
main one that we're going to focus on as
well as some of the the liver enzymes
looking at inflammation.
And we've got the average result here.
And then we've got the uh standard
deviation or the overall spread of the
data. And then here I guess they've got
percentages or whatever doesn't have a
mean gets put in the middle. Just weird.
and it just gets worse unfortunately.
Uh in terms of the dietary intake during
the intervention, you can see some of
the changes, you know, like protein
levels were slightly higher in the
experimental diet. Um the saturated fat
was obviously lower because that's what
they specifically switched out.
Monounsatur I guess polyunsaturated fats
were increased. Um carbohydrates were
just a tick lower for the experimental
condition. uh fiber was was higher in
the experimental condition and uh yeah I
guess that's just it fiber in gram form
or in percentage form now unfortunately
I mean this does create a lot of
confounding unfortunately we can't now
say because you're seeing differences in
fiber for example you're seeing
differences in carbohydrate intake
you're seeing differences in protein
intake that does suddenly start to
create some confounding where it's like
well I like how can we make any sort of
conclusion specifically about canola oil
even though they use canola oil to be
one of the constituents of the ex this
experimental diet. Yeah. I mean again
just bad design if that's what you're
trying to figure out.
Okay. So now here's our data from the
the baseline versus 8 weeks later. And
we see baseline and eight weeks later
reflected here in this P1 for the
control diet and for the experimental
diet. So P1 is the within groups
comparison, baseline versus 8 weeks. The
P2 is for the experimental diet,
baseline versus 8 weeks later. And then
we've got P3, which is the between
groups comparison. That's where we
should be focused our attention on. We
can then look at the within groups if we
want to. But the point is here that we
do see a slight increase in body weight
in the control diet and we see no change
in the experimental diet but it is
statistically significant. So the
control diet saw an increase in body
weight. Um
various ways of interpreting that uh but
it just again you could argue that it's
kind of feeding into the confounding
of the study. You could argue that
that's just a part of the diet. It just
leads to to more weight gain, which
would may be harmful. You could go a
bunch of different directions. Overall,
however, on the control diet, we don't
see any other changes except for, I
guess, triglycerides
increased slightly as well. On the other
hand, when we look at the experimental
diet, we see that total cholesterol was
decreased. LDL cholesterol was decreased
in Apo B. So, a more sensitive marker of
LDL uh was also decreased and it was
statistically significant between
groups. It's also the case for the tri
triglycerides if I remember. Yeah, for
triglycerides as well. Finally when we
look at the actual so some like TNF
receptor I I okay interlucan 6 high
sensitivity CRP uh interfuron gamma
these are all four of these are
inflammatory markers and none of them
change in any of the conditions nothing
changes so the point being that this
kind of bastardized version of this
canola oil diet uh led to no it led to
only improvements in health uh across a
few different metrics, but uh the
inflammation metrics did not budge. So,
no improvement, no worsening, and
there's where we can leave that. Okay,
let's get into the heated canola oil on
inflammation. So, this is going to be
different from the other studies. And
there's, as far as I'm aware, there's
only been one study up to this point, I
should say randomized control trial
that's been done, or intervention trial
that's been done on this topic. And it's
study 408. You can see that it's a mixed
funding. You can also see that there are
a number of different conditions. So the
researchers are com comparing virgin
olive oil, sunflower oil, or a grouping.
This is a bit of a Frankenstein version
of a study where they used mixed seed
oil. So this mixed seed oil is 70%
canola, so largely canola, and 30%
sunflower oil. And then they've added
either these natural phenols to protect
as antioxidants or they've added
dimethyl polyeloxane.
Okay, so I didn't know anything about
dimethyl polyeloxane,
but apparently the researchers write it
down as an antioxidant. And then I
looked into it and I have a really hard
time finding it as a normal antioxidant.
I've seen uh very few reports as it as
an antioxidant. So I'm a little doubtful
of how that's being framed. Uh what I
have found related to it is that it's
often mixed with seed oils especially in
the frying process to lessen the
frothing that occurs or the foaming that
occurs from the uh seed oil processing.
So it is uh a realworld scenario I
suppose in that uh a person might be
consuming uh very tiny levels of this
dimethyl polyeloxane
uh when consuming a processed or highly
processed I suppose I should say more
like fried and highly processed version
of uh seed oil. So, it does have real
world applicability, but I just don't
know if I'd necessarily agree with the
framing that the researchers use of it
being an antioxidant. There's some kind
of kind of sideways, indirect ways that
it could potentially be an antioxidant,
but it's not an antioxidant in the terms
like these phenols are, which are direct
antioxidants.
Uh also just as a final thing from my
reading on on dimethyl dimethyl
polyiloxane
is that it is absorbed in very tiny
amounts into the body. The rest of it is
excreted. So the primary effect would uh
happen throughout the intestinal tract.
Okay. So we can see that there's no
placebo here but it is randomized and
there's no blinding. It's kind of
difficult to do when you don't have a
placebo. It's a two-eek treatment and
it's also a crossover design as in we
have the same 20 participants 49 to 63
years old old obese but don't have any
other uh health issues other than uh
being overweight. And these same
individuals get exposed to each of these
conditions. And to walk you through the
heating process, what they do is they
heat the oils up to 180°
uh 180° Celsius if I remember correctly.
Yeah, 180° C. So, it's about 356°
Fahrenheit for 5 minutes in a deep
fryer. And they do that uh 10 times each
day for 2 days, resulting in a total of
20 heating cycles. And then they give
this uh this highly heated 20 times over
uh oils which happens to all these
conditions to the participants to
consume and then they measure over 4
hours what happens to their inflammatory
profile. So that's what we're going to
be uh going over. All right. To explain
this, this is uh the IAPA
IAPA beta pathway. I guess we'll we'll
we'll just keep it pretty simple. Um
there's this complex of proteins that's
found within your cells and they're
upstream of a protein that is called
NFCAPPA beta. And this protein when it's
set loose, when it's free to move around
your cells, it will what's known as
transllocate. So it'll move from the
cytool so where it's captured uh and
then when it's released like uh the
genie out of the bottle it will move to
the nucleus where your genes are kept
and typically not always but typically
it binds to pro-inflammatory genes
meaning that then this NFCappa beta once
free will then bind to these genes and
lead to greater expression or production
of uh the proteins that are associated
with those genes.
So we've looked at other
pro-inflammatory proteins like
interlucan one uh interlucan 6 TNF alpha
things of that nature. That's what we're
talking about here. So this NFCAPPA beta
would enter the the nucleus bind those
genes lead to greater expression. So the
production of more of these proteins
which would then lead to a more
pro-inflammatory state. These proteins
are upstream of that NFCappa beta and
typically if they're increased there's a
lot of nuance here and typically you
would want more data than what we're
looking at here but if these are
increased that indicates typically that
you have more of this free NFCAPPA beta.
So the NFCappa beta can then act as this
pro-inflammatory.
And to walk you through, there's a bunch
of different comparisons, but
ultimately, uh, we're looking at the
comparisons between like baseline and 4
hours later, and some of the comparisons
are like 4 hours versus 2 hours later,
things of that nature. So, the VO is the
virgin olive oil. Then the SFO is the
sunflower oil, and keep in mind that's
just sunflower oil alone. Then we have
the mixed seed oil which is primarily
canola oil with this dimethyl
polyeloxane
which I'm going to now call the D
molecule because I don't want to keep
having to repeat that name. And that's
the SOD condition here. And then the SOP
or SOP is the same mixed seed oils plus
uh the addition. So without the D
molecule but including these phenolic
compounds. uh and the these phenolic
compounds by the way also come from
olive oil. So residue from from the
olive oil. So this is uh with the
traditional antioxidants.
And what we can see here is that the
sunflower oil and the uh sod, so the
canola oil plus sunflower oil plus this
de molecule tend to see increases not in
every situation but tend to see
increases in these inflammatory
proteins, these intracellular
uh proteins. On the other hand, when you
look at olive oil or if you consume this
uh canola oil
plus the addition of the phenolic
compounds, we no longer see that
elevation in these inflammatory
proteins. So, this is uh pretty
interesting, but again, this is
intracellular proteins. We probably want
to look at some more of the factors that
we looked at earlier. again the actual
proteins that cause this inflammation
itself which to the rest of the body
which is like interlucan 6 and things
and proteins of that nature. So here we
are. We have interlucan 1 beta,
interlucan 6. Those are the two that
we've seen before. And then they've also
looked at MIF and junk one. I'm not
going to focus on these as much uh
simply because they are again uh we're
generally talking about signaling within
the cell. These are signaling outside of
the cell. Not that they pro they
probably have intracellular effects as
well, but uh we're most concerned with
their extracellular. So once they've
been kicked out of the cell. Also keep
in mind that we're looking at gene
expression. So this is not measurements
of actual protein. I've said this many
times before, but there are instances
where you can see increases in gene
expression and then see no changes in
protein. Typically that's not the case,
but I'm just throwing that out there
because I've said it multiple times
before. When we just look at gene
expression, it's it's we'll say 90% of
the time it'll lead to increases in
protein expression or protein levels.
but not always. Okay. So that said here
they do a comparison for interlucan 1
beta and they do indicate that with this
sunflower oil condition that we see
increases in uh interlucan one beta uh
at the 4hour mark unlike the 2-hour
mark. So comparing the 2hour versus
4hour we see an increase. uh you might
you could maybe argue that that would
also be the case if you were to look at
this canola oil condition uh simply but
again we've got 20 individuals you can
see that the standard error bars are
pretty wide so is it possible that if
they'd had more participants that they
would have seen an effect yeah it's
definitely possible I'd be open to that
argument um but as it stands what we
know is that that the sunflower oil when
that is heated repeatedly without any
sort sort of antioxidants added that it
leads to this increase in interlucan 1
beta and the same is true when looking
at uh interlucan 6 and we see similar
stories when it comes to uh the mif and
junk one or jk1 uh that typically we see
increases and this one seems to be a lot
more uh in relation so this is an
intracellular protein just to be clear
it's it's a little bit like these
proteins um so it's not as telling as
these two proteins over here. But it is
still a signal that we should pay
attention to. And we see that the canola
oil condition plus sunflower plus uh
this D molecule seems to have an
increase in these inflammatory profiles.
Again, in every instance, however, the
olive oil and the canola oil plus the
antioxidant added to it, the phenolic
compounds, we do not see uh these
effects. So interesting and certainly
speaks to the potential that uh heating
oils over and over again can lead to
detrimental effects. Of course, this
study doesn't have particular controls.
That would be nice to see. Uh for
example, you would want to see a
comparison versus like a cold canola
oil. Uh a cold safflower oil. Uh you
would like to see less of a mixture of
these oils. I mean, it's really
difficult to tease out differences
between them. I would have also liked to
have seen a canola oil condition where
they heat it without any sort of
additions like the final compounds or
the de molecule uh just because it's
hard to tease out uh where the effect is
if it's directly related to canola oil.
My impression is that it's you know
canola oil or or another thing is that
this mixture of safflower sunflower oil
sorry and um the uh canola oil we see
that in the sunflower oil we see
increases in these uh interlucans. So is
it the 30% sunflower that's in that
mixed combination and then the canola
oil has no effect. It's you know a lot
of these things are tough to tease out
when you don't have proper control. So,
this is, as I said, it's a bit of a
Frankenstein study, and it's kind of
just mashed together. Uh, I I think that
if they had done if they tried to do
less but tried to do it better, I think
this would have been a better study.
Still, regardless, we can definitely say
that heating these oils over and over
still leads to an increase in these
inflammatory molecules. This still
doesn't tell us if we have changes in
outcomes, which is something that we
would love to see. uh some other markers
that they didn't test. Uh they just
looked at these particular proteins,
which again still tells us something,
but I'd like to see a lot more. Another
question that's on my mind is what
happens when you just heat one time?
Most people when they cook, most people
when they uh use these oils, then
they're going to be cooking it just
once. They're just going to be using it
once. So, do we still see these
increases? I don't know. I mean, we're
looking at 20 times uh being heated over
and over and over again. So,
there's a lot of outstanding questions
uh coming from a uh kind of poor study
design. That said, one final thing I'll
quick point out is potentially with the
frying process that occurs. I don't know
how often in uh like fast food joints or
whatever that or kitchens in general
that commercial kitchens I'm talking
about that they replace the oils. maybe
they don't replace them often at all and
in that situation this would be a lot
more applicable still a poor study but
still a lot more applicable and in that
situation yeah it does indicate that we
see uh increases in some inflammatory
profiles which is interesting so uh the
vast majority of intervention studies
keep in mind we've just been focused on
intervention studies indicate that
canola oil is either neutral or reduces
inflammatory markers in humans so we're
talking about cold canola oil. Uh, and
then there's this one short-term study
over 4 hours that indicates when
repeatedly heated that the canola oil
might raise inflammatory markers. Uh,
again, really tough to isolate there
because the poor study design and the
fact that they're mixing canola oil with
sunflower oil. But still as it stands uh
this does indicate that if you
repeatedly heat 20 times over uh canola
oil or a mixture of this these seed oils
canola oil plus sunflower oil without
any phenolic compounds so no
antioxidants that you would experience
an increase in these inflammatory
molecules which is interesting. One more
thing I'll quick add here. Uh, so I
guess to to make this more applicable,
let me quick turn to just me real quick.
So to make this more applicable, um the
way that I would frame things currently
based off of these intervention trials
and
I've looked at uh long-term trials which
are epidemiological, but specifically
focusing on this looking at canola oil
and looking at these intervention
trials, it indicates to me that
consuming cold canola oil will either be
a positive or neutral to your
inflammatory state. On the other hand,
consuming with very limited evidence,
but still indicating that way that if
you consume canola oil after you've been
he consistently consume it uh when it's
been heated over and over and over
again, that would probably be something
that you should consider avoiding. Um,
and where's that probably going to be
the case? When it comes to like
restaurants and whatnot. Um, so
the other final thing that I'll point
out is that we didn't see even with this
uh this repeated heating of the canola
oil. Keep in mind that when you're
consuming food, you're not just
consuming uh canola oil, which in this
situation they fed it through, I think
muffins was, and before people say,
well, maybe it's the muffins that are
causing this issue. Um, the muffins were
identical across the board except for
differences in these uh in these fats.
So, it seems unlikely that it's the
muffins themselves and more so that it's
the actual oils themselves. The actual
canola oil and the uh the sunflower oil.
Yeah, muffins and skim milk uh were
prepared with these uh oils. Okay. So,
if you consume
these canola oil that's been heated
repeatedly, but you're also consuming a
high antioxidant diet, a high
antioxidant meal, let's say, let's just
focus on the meal. Uh, there's a
potential that you wouldn't see any of
these negative effects. I don't know
that for a fact because still this
study, I'll repeat it for like the third
or fourth time. It's just such a poor
design that it's hard to extrapolate
that. What we do know for sure is that
the co-conumption with antioxidants
seems to get rid of all these
inflammatory situations. So this seems
like a hypersp specific situation where
you're you're maybe if you're going to a
restaurant, they're heating it over and
over and over again. You eat it as
you're probably not going to eat just
straight oil, which is
highly unlikely, right? um after it's
been heated. You might eat straight oil
if you're going to use it for like a
salad or something like that, but at
that point it's not been heated over and
over. This is cold. So, we've already
addressed that. That's not an issue. But
the issue is when it's heated over and
over, then uh if you're consuming it as
just straight fried food, if you look at
your plate and it's just all fried food
with like fries and u I don't know,
fried chicken or whatever. I I'm just
like coming up with random foods, but it
can be a whole host of different foods
and there's no antioxidants there, then
yeah, this would be a lot more
applicable. Um, however, if you're
looking at your food and one of the
foods has been fried in canola oil and
the other foods or lots of greens, I
don't know what your plate looks like,
but if you're consuming a lot of greens,
we have some indication that that might
not be as much a risk from a canola oil
perspective. I'm still not I'm certainly
not saying that fried food is good for
you uh or that you're eliminating the
negatives of fried foods, but from this
angle, the inflammatory angle of canola
oil, that may not be as much of an
issue. So hopefully that's somewhat
clear, hopefully that offers a little
bit of uh clarity to you. And uh if
you'd like to continue this
investigation with me, I have an
extended version of this video uh for
improving canola oils effects and that's
in the physionic insiders as you well
know if you've been following my work.
Um we'll have to see what future studies
hopefully we can get more studies on
heated canola oil specifically looking
at canola oil instead of doing a mixture
and uh then we'll get some some greater
clarity on the topic. But you know, so
far at least we have one study that
indicates that that uh there may be some
reason for caution in specific
instances.
Okay. Well, if you're going to be
joining me for the extended version,
then uh click the link below uh for the
and join the Physionic Insiders. You'll
get access to this plus a ton more. A
ton more, like a ridiculous amount more.
And otherwise, I'll catch you in the
next one. Thanks for hanging out.